帝
国
客
黑
阵
矩
革
命
没有任何发现  长官
I got nothing, sir.
没有奈奥比和幽灵的踪迹
No sign of Niobe or Ghost.
全是没拔掉插头的人
Nothing but blue pills.
要不要主动联系他们
Should we try to contact them?
没必要了  我感觉他们已经被击落了
Won't matter. My gut says they're down.
那就返航吧
We should start back.
不  只要它还能飞  对我们就有用
No, if that ship can fly, we need it.
就怕你这么说
I was afraid you'd say that.
搜索所有已知的管道  洞口和裂缝
Search every pipe, every hole, every crack we know.
尽量用最短的时间搜索最大的区域
Sweep as wide as possible, as fast as possible.
舰长  管道里全是乌贼
Captain, these lines are crawling with calamari.
那就尽快找到他们
The sooner we find them the better.
-你该吃点东西了  -谢谢
- Thought you could use something to eat. - Thank you.
有好转吗
Any change?
没有
No.
-他怎么样  -没什么大碍
- How is he? - He's gonna be fine.
至少他醒来之前没事
At least until he wakes up.
-什么意思  -舰长有问题问他
- What do you mean? - Captain has some questions for him.
他最好能回答上来
He'd better have some good answers.
看到这些伤口没  应该是他自己划的
You see these cuts? I think they're self-inflicted.
-为什么  -震颤谵妄  说不好
- Why? - VDTs maybe. I don't know.
植物神经功能紊乱
但他最好能解释清楚
But like I said, the answer better be good.
罗兰  再搜索一遍矩阵吧
Roland, I'd like to run another search through the Matrix.
-为什么  -为了尼奥
- For what? - For Neo.
他没有插上插头  怎么可能在矩阵里  长官
How could he be in the Matrix, sir? He's not plugged in.
拜托了  帮我个忙
Please, for me.
我一直想不明白
This is what keeps bothering me.
什么
What?
他的神经活动和其他昏迷的人不同
His neural patterns don't read like someone who's in a coma.
奇怪的是  这种活动我还经常见到
The strange thing is, I see these patterns all the time.
-在哪见到  -进入矩阵的人
- Where? - On someone jacked in.
一无所获  他不在矩阵里
The big bupkes. Nada. He's not in there.
-长官  我收到预报了  -还有多久
- Sir, I got the projections. - How long?
根据钻点和之前的速度
Based on point of entry and the past speed,
二十小时后敌军将抵达锡安
the machines will be in Zion in 20 hours.
我的天
Jesus H. Christ.
好吧  大家各就各位
All right, let's move with a purpose.
AK  上楼  你负责全息监测
AK, get upstairs, I want you on holographics.
毛瑟  舰首舰尾的炮台随时待命
Mauser, I want forward and aft guns manned at all times.
启动的悬浮推进器越少越好
And make sure we are running on as few pads as possible.
-有人呼叫  -什么
- Hey! You got a call. - What?
接线员
Operator.
是赛拉弗
It's Seraph.
先知让我带个话  你们必须马上来
I bring word from the Oracle. You must come at once.
早上好
Good morning.
-你是谁  -我叫萨蒂  我知道你是尼奥
- Who are you? - My name is Sati. Your name is Neo.
边境大道
爸爸说你不该出现在这
My papa says you're not supposed to be here.
他说你一定是迷路了
He says you must be lost.
你迷路了吗  尼奥
Are you lost, Neo?
-我在哪儿  -这里是车站
- Where am I? - This is the train station.
-不是矩阵吗  -这里的车通向矩阵
- This isn't the Matrix? - That's where the train goes.
我们正要去  但你不能和我们一起
That's where we're going, but you cannot go with us.
-为什么  -他不准
- Why not? - He won't let you.
-谁不准  -"火车人"  我不喜欢他
- Who won't? - The Trainman. I don't like him.
但爸爸说我们得照他说的做
But my papa says we have to do what the Trainman says
不然他就把我们永远留在这里
or else he will leave us here forever and ever.
墨菲斯  崔妮蒂  感谢你们的到来
Morpheus, Trinity, thank you for coming.
这么多年来我明白了一个道理
One thing I've learned in all my years
事情总是不能尽如人意
is that nothing ever works out the way you want it to.
-你是谁  -我是先知
- Who are you? - I'm the Oracle.
我也希望有个好的解决方案  可是没有
I wish there was an easy way to get through this, but there ain't.
很抱歉走到了这步
I'm sorry this had to happen.
我也希望能像以前一样安坐在这
I'm sorry I couldn't be sitting here like you remember me
-可我注定要走到这步  -发生了什么
- but it wasn't meant to be. - What happened?
我做了一个选择  而这个选择的代价
I made a choice, and that choice cost me
超乎我的想象
more than I wanted it to.
什么选择
What choice?
帮助你  引导尼奥
To help you, to guide Neo.
而现在我真正的考验在于
Now, since the real test for any choice
明知这么做可能付出的代价
is having to make the same choice again,
仍要再次作出同样的选择
knowing full well what it might cost.
我应该觉得之前的选择还不错
I guess I feel pretty good about that choice,
因为我又选择了帮助你们
because here I am, at it again.
-你知道尼奥怎么了吗  -知道
- Do you know what happened to Neo? - Yes.
他被困在一个
He is trapped in a place
介于矩阵和机器世界之间的地方
between this world and the machine world.
那里被一个叫火车人的程序控制
The link is controlled by a program called the Trainman.
那是他向矩阵走私程序的渠道
He uses it to smuggle programs in and out of the Matrix.
如果他在你之前发现尼奥
If he finds out where Neo is before you get to him
恐怕届时我们的选择会变得无比艰难
then I'm afraid our choices are going to become difficult.
-为什么  -因为火车人的老板
- Why? - Because of who the Trainman works for.
梅洛文基恩
The Merovingian.
他开重金悬赏你们
He has placed a bounty on your lives.
一定要时刻警惕
You must be careful at all times.
赛拉弗知道怎么找到火车人  他会带你们去
Seraph knows how to find the Trainman. He'll go with you.
他已经保护了我很多年
For years he has protected me.
希望也能保护你们
I hope he can do the same for you.
请跟我来
Please, follow me.
先知
Oracle.
我知道  墨菲斯
I know, Morpheus.
看的出你内心满是疑惑不解
I can see you're filled with doubt, clouded by uncertainty.
发生了这么多事以后
After everything that has happened,
你还指望我会相信你吗
how can you expect me to believe you?
我不指望
I don't.
一直以来  我只指望着一件事
I expect just what I've always expected:
不管你信不信我  快拿定主意
for you to make up your own damn mind. Believe me or don't.
我只能告诉你
All I can do is tell you that
你的朋友有麻烦了  他需要你的帮助
your friend is in trouble, and he needs your help.
他需要大家的帮助
He needs all our help.
-你从矩阵来吗  -是的
- Are you from the Matrix? - Yes.
不
No.
-以前是  -那为什么要离开矩阵呢
- I mean, I was. - Why did you leave?
-我必须离开  -我也不得不离开家
- I had to. - I had to leave my home too.
萨蒂  过来  亲爱的  让那个可怜人自己待会
Sati! Come here, darling. Leave the poor man in peace.
好的  爸爸
Yes, Papa.
抱歉  她好奇心一直这么强
I am sorry. She is still very curious.
-我见过你  -是的  在法国人的餐厅里
- I know you. - Yes, in the restaurant of the Frenchman.
我是拉玛·坎德拉  这是我的妻子  卡玛拉
I am Rama-Kandra. This is my wife, Kamala.
我的女儿  萨蒂
My daughter, Sati.
见到你无比荣幸
We are most honored to meet you.
-你们都是程序  -是的
- You are programs. - Oh, yes.
我管理发电厂的循环系统
I am the power-plant systems manager for recycling operations.
我妻子是交互界面程序员
My wife is an interactive software programmer.
她极富有创造性
She is highly creative.
你来这里干什么  你不属于这
What are you doing here? You do not belong here.
卡玛拉  天哪  抱歉  我妻子说话很直
Kamala! Goodness, I apologize. My wife can be very direct.
没关系
It's okay.
我也不知道为什么
I don't have an answer.
-我连这是哪儿都不知道  -哪儿都不是
- I don't even know where "Here" Is. - This place is nowhere.
在你的世界和我们的世界之间
It is between your world and our world.
-火车人是什么人  -他为法国佬工作
- Who's the Trainman? - He works for the Frenchman.
我居然一点都不惊讶
Why did I know you would say that?
法国佬心胸狭窄  睚眦必报
The Frenchman does not forget, and he does not forgive.
-你了解他  -我只了解我需要知道的
- You know him? - I know only what I need to know.
我知道如果想把矩阵外的东西
I know that if you want to take something
送进矩阵
from our world into your world
就得找那个法国人
that does not belong there, you must go to the Frenchman.
你们就是要进去吗
Is that what you're doing here?
-拉玛  别说了  -别这么无情  卡玛拉
- Rama, please. - I do not want to be cruel, Kamala.
他可能这辈子都见不到别人了
He may never see another face for the rest of his life.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
-你可以不回答的  -没关系
- You don't have to answer that question. - No, I don't mind.
答案很简单
The answer is simple.
我非常爱我的女儿
I love my daughter very much.
她是我这辈子最美丽的结晶
I find her to be the most beautiful thing I have ever seen.
但机器可不管这个
But where we are from, that is not enough.
每个程序都必须有自己的作用
Every program that is created must have a purpose.
没有用处  就会被删除
If it does not, it is deleted.
为了救我女儿  我去找了法国人
I went to the Frenchman to save my daughter.
-你似乎很疑惑  -我从没...
- You do not understand. - I just have never...
听程序说过"爱"
Heard a program speak of love.
-这是人类的情感  -不  这只是一个词
- It is a human emotion. - No, it is a word.
重要的是这个词所蕴含的联系
What matters is the connection the word implies.
看得出你也爱着别人
I see that you are in love.
能告诉我为了维持那种联系
Can you tell me what you would give
你愿意付出什么吗
to hold on to that connection?
一切
Anything.
那或许你来这的原因
Then perhaps the reason you are here
和我也没什么不同
is not so different than the reason I am here.
就是他
That's him.
-滚开  离我远点  -我们不想惹麻烦
- Get away! Get away from me! - We don't want trouble.
-都他妈离我远点  -我们需要你的帮助
- Get the hell away from me! - We need your help.
我帮不了你们  谁都帮不了
I can't help you! No one can help you!
不好
Oh, no!
该死
Damn it!
-车什么时候来  -已经晚点了
- When is the train due? - It is already late.
火车人通常可不会迟到
It's not like the Trainman to be late.
-跟我有关系吗  -说不准
- You think it has something to do with me? - I cannot say.
这种事只有先知知道
Who knows such things? Only the Oracle.
-你还认识先知  -所有人都认识先知
- You know the Oracle? - Everyone knows the Oracle.
在找法国人之前我还咨询了她
I consulted with her before I met with the Frenchman.
她答应在我们离开之后照看萨蒂
She promised to watch Sati after we said goodbye.
离开
Goodbye?
-你们不跟她一起吗  -不可能的
- You're not staying with her? - It is not possible.
法国人只答应送我们女儿去
Our arrangement with the Frenchman was for our daughter only.
-我妻子和我都得回去  -为什么
- My wife and I must return to our world. - Why?
-这是我们的报应  -你相信因果报应
- That is our karma. - You believe in karma?
和爱一样  只是一个词
Karma is a word, like love.
一种表明"我来这里干什么"的方式
A way of saying: "What I am here to do."
我不仅不排斥我的报应  还很感激它
I do not resent my karma. I'm grateful for it.
感激我美好的生活  和我美丽的女儿
Grateful for my wonderful wife, for my beautiful daughter.
他们是上天的恩赐
They are gifts,
所以我绝对不能辜负他们
and so I do what I must do to honor them.
-爸爸  车来了  -好的  快拿上你的包
- Papa, the train! - Yes. Find your bag. Quickly.
能帮你拎一个吗
Can I carry that for you?
好吧
All right.
赶紧的  我已经迟到了
Hurry it up, I'm late!
-你是谁  -一个朋友  -拉玛
- Who are you? - He is a friend.  - Rama?
我认识你
I know you.
-原来他们是来找你的  -我得回去
- So that's what they wanted. - I need to get back.
要什么我都给你
I'll pay you whatever you want.
不论如何  我要上这列车
One way or another, I'm getting on this train.
不  不  不
Oh, no, no, no.
梅洛文基恩开口之前你得一直待在这
You'll stay here until the Merovingian says different.
以我对他的了解  你得待好一阵了
If I know him, you're gonna be here for a long, long time.
-别逼我动粗  -还不明白
- I don't want to hurt you. - You don't get it.
这里是我建的
I built this place.
在这里  规矩由我定  只有我威胁别人的份
Down here, I make the rules. Down here, I make the threats.
在这里  我就是上帝
Down here, I'm God.
上车  不然就留在这陪他
Get on the train or you'll stay here with him.
我们应该回去再问问先知  她知道该怎么做
We should return to the Oracle. She will know what to do.
不  我们自己心里有数
No. We know what has to be done.
该死
Shit.
开玩笑的吧
You gotta be kidding.
我操  居然是下凡天使
Holy shit, it's wingless.
我明白了
I get it.
你是来送死的吧
You must be ready to die.
我得和他谈谈
I need to speak with him.
想进这扇门
Only way you're getting through this door
除非我死了
is over my big, dead ass.
那好吧
So be it.
俱乐部里禁止携带武器
There are no weapons allowed in the club.
电梯到底层时  有个寄存外衣的姑娘
At the bottom of this elevator, there is a coat-check girl
运气好的话  还有个检查武器的人
and if we are lucky, one man for checking weapons.
运气不好呢
And if we're unlucky?
会有好多人
There will be many men.
我能帮您保管...天哪
Can I take your...? Oh, my God.
这是干什么
What in the hell?
难以置信
I don't believe this.
无翼的天使[法语]  浪子回头了
The prodigal child returns. L'ange sans ses ailes.
你是为赏金而来的吗  赛拉弗
Are you here for the bounty, Seraph?
你们的枪里还剩多少子弹
Tell me, how many bullets are there in those guns?
虽然我不知道  但估计不够吧
I don't know, but I don't think you have enough.
-我们只想谈谈  -是吗
- We only want to talk. - Oh, yes.
你们真是迫切  不惜一路杀进我的领地
I'm sure you do. You have fought through Hel to do so. Yes?
告诉你们该怎么做吧
I'll tell you what I will do.
把枪放下  我答应放你们活着出去
Put down the guns, and I will promise you a safe passage out of here.
-我们三个  -是的  是的
- All three of us? - Oh, yes, yes.
当然
Of course.
谁知道上次见面之后没多久
Who could have guessed we would see each other so soon
我们就再会了
after our last meeting?
造化弄人啊
The Fates are too kind, eh?
而你  我的犹大  带他们来找到我
And since you, my little Judas, have brought them here.
我猜那个算命的
I can only surmise that
又找到了一副新的肉身吧
the fortuneteller has found herself another shell?
真失望  但并不意外
Disappointing, but not unexpected.
不过我还是希望
I do hope, however,
她能记住之前的教训
she has the good manners to learn her lesson
知道一切的行为都有相应的后果
and to remember that there is no action without consequence.
从我这拿了东西  就得付出代价
And if you take something from me, you will pay the price.
你知道我们来这的原因
You know why we are here?
得了吧  这算什么问题  我当然知道
Come now, what kind of question is this? Of course I know.
我就是干这行的
It is my business to know.
有人认为是巧合  我可不觉得
Some might think this is a strange coincidence, but I do not.
不过我还是很好奇  他是怎么进去的
I am curious, though, as to how it actually happened.
-你们知道吗  -不
- Do you know? - No.
不
No?
不会吧
I did not think so.
但问问总没错  对吧
But it is always best to ask, huh?
我们想做个交易
We want to make a deal.
总是开门见山呢  墨菲斯
Always straight to business, huh, Morpheus?
好吧  我有你们要的东西
Okay. I have something you want.
要做交易  你们也得有我要的东西  对吗
To make a deal, you must have something I want, yes?
正好我想要一样东西
And it so happens there is something I want.
我刚到这里时就想要了
Something I have wanted ever since I first came here.
据说不能强取  只能被赐予
It is said they cannot be taken, they can only be given.
什么
What?
先知的眼睛
The eyes of the Oracle.
我告诉过你
I told you before,
一切事物都得遵循自然的规律
there is no escaping the nature of the universe.
是自然规律让我们再次见面
It is that nature that has again brought you to me.
别人觉得是巧合  我则认为是必然的结果
Where some see coincidence, I see consequence.
别人以为是运气  我看到了代价
Where others see chance, I see cost.
把先知的眼睛交给我
Bring me the eyes of the Oracle
我就把救世主还给你们
and I will give you back your savior.
我觉得这个交易公平合理
It seems a perfectly fair and reasonable deal to me.
行还是不行
Yes? No?
没时间跟你废话
I don't have time for this shit.
想做交易吗  这样吧
You wanna make a deal? How about this?
交出尼奥  不然现在就同归于尽
You give me Neo, or we all die, right here, right now.
这交易有意思
Interesting deal.
你真的准备为他付出生命吗
You are really ready to die for this man?
-不信吗  -她下得去手
- Believe it. - She'll do it.
她不惜杀了这里所有人
If she has to, she'll kill every one of us.
她陷入爱河了
She's in love.
真是神奇
It is remarkable how similar
恋爱中的人做事就和疯子一样
the pattern of love is to the pattern of insanity.
时间到
Time's up.
怎么样  梅文
What's it gonna be, Merv?
好吧  你能自己进来
Okay. You got yourself in here
也能把自己弄出去
you can get yourself out.
准备好了吗
Are you ready for us?
差不多了  长官  这里有不少古老的漏洞
Almost, sir. They got some pretty ancient hacks here.
我们正在破解
We're working on them.
-你们找到尼奥了吗  -你看不见他吗
- But you found Neo? - Can't you see him?
看不见  看得到编码  却认不出来
No, sir. We read something, but I couldn't tell what.
我还不能走
I can't leave yet.
我得见她一面
I have to see her.
现在吗
Now?
这是我最后的机会
It's my last chance.
这就对了  这就是秘诀
That's it. That's the secret.
-得用手认真揉  -为什么
- You've got to use your hands. - Why?
饼干也需要倾注爱
Cookies need love like everything does.
尼奥
Neo!
我还以为能赶在你来之前做完呢
I was hoping to have these done before you got here.
既然这样
Oh, well.
萨蒂  亲爱的  可以尝尝了
Sati, honey, I think it's time for a tasting.
拿着碗去找赛拉弗  看做好了没
Take the bowl to Seraph and find out if they're ready.
好的
Okay.
-你能出来我很高兴  -我也是
- I'm glad you got out. - Me too.
还认得我吗
So do you recognize me?
-能认出一部分  -对  就是这么回事
- A part of you. - Yeah, that's how it works.
失去一些  留下一些
Some bits you lose, some bits you keep.
现在我还认不出镜中的自己
I don't yet recognize my face in the mirror...
但我还爱吃糖果
but I still love candy.
不了  谢谢
No, thank you.
记得你第一次来见我时的样子吗
Remember how you were when you first walked through my door?
战战兢兢不知所措  而现在  看看你
Jittery as a June bug. And now, just look at you.
你总能给我惊喜  尼奥  现在也是
You sure did surprise me, Neo, and you still do.
你也给了我不少惊喜
You gave me a few surprises too.
希望我帮到你了
I hope I helped.
你帮我走到这一步
You helped me to get here,
但我的问题是  为什么
but my question is, why?
事态会如何发展
Where is this going?
-会如何结束  -我不知道
- Where does it end? - I don't know.
-你不知道还是不想说  -我告诉过你
- You don't know or you won't tell me? - I told you before...
自己都无法理解的选择
no one can see beyond a choice
永远看不到结果  无论是谁
they don't understand, and I mean no one.
-什么选择  -这不重要  是我做的选择
- What choice? - It doesn't matter. It's my choice.
我要做出选择  你也一样
I have mine to make, same as you have yours.
跟我说什么话你也要选择吗
Does that include what things to tell me and what not to?
当然不
Of course not.
那为什么没告诉我架构师的事
Then why didn't you tell me about the Architect?
为什么不告诉我
Why didn't you tell me about
锡安和以前的救世主们的事
Zion and the ones before me?
为什么不告诉我真相
Why didn't you tell me the truth?
因为还不是告诉你的时候
Because it wasn't time for you to know.
这时机由谁决定
Who decided it wasn't time?
你知道是谁
You know who.
拉丁文Temet Nosce
英文Know Thyself
意为认识你自己
是我
I did.
我觉得该多了解一些事了
Then I think it's time for me to know a few more things.
我也是
So do I.
为什么我没有进入矩阵
Tell me how I separated my mind
意识却和身体分离了
from my body without jacking in.
我是怎么通过意念阻止四只哨兵的
Tell me how I stopped four sentinels by thinking it.
我这到底是怎么了
Tell me just what the hell is happening to me.
救世主的力量不只限于这个世界
The power of the One extends beyond this world.
他的力量从这里一直延伸到它的发源地
It reaches from here all the way back to where it came from.
-哪里  -源头
- Where? - The source.
当你碰触哨兵时
That's what you felt when you touched
你感觉到了  但你还没准备好
those sentinels, but you weren't ready for it.
你本该送命的
You should be dead,
可你也没准备好去死
but apparently you weren't ready for that either.
架构师说如果我不回到源头
The Architect said that if I didn't return to the source,
锡安将在今天午夜时分被毁灭
Zion would be destroyed by midnight tonight.
得了吧
Please.
你和我可能只看不透自己的选择
You and I may not be able to see beyond our own choices...
但他什么选择都看不透
but that man can't see past any choice.
-为什么  -他不理解选择  他没法理解
- Why not? - He doesn't understand them. He can't.
对他而言  它们只是方程中的变量
To him, they are variables in an equation.
必须一个一个地解出  配平
One at a time, each variable must be solved, then countered.
这就是他的目的  保持方程的平衡
That's his purpose. To balance the equation.
你的目的是什么
What's your purpose?
打破平衡
To unbalance it.
为什么  你想要什么
Why? What do you want?
和你一样  尼奥
I want the same thing you want, Neo.
而且我和你一样愿意为此付出一切
And I'm willing to go as far as you are to get it.
为了结束战争
The end of the war.
战争会结束吗
Is it going to end?
总会结束的
One way or another.
能保住锡安吗
Can Zion be saved?
抱歉  我不知道这个问题的答案  但是
I'm sorry, I don't have the answer to that question, but...
如果真有答案
if there is an answer,
你只能在一个地方找到
there's only one place you're going to find it.
-哪里  -你知道是哪里
- Where? - You know where.
如果你找不到答案
And if you can't find the answer...
恐怕我们大家都不会有未来了
then I'm afraid there may be no tomorrow for any of us.
这是什么意思
What does that mean?
万物有始者
Everything that has a beginning...
即有终
has an end.
我看到了终点
I see the end coming.
黑暗正在蔓延
I see the darkness spreading.
我看到了死亡
I see death.
而能阻止他的只有你
And you are all that stands in his way.
史密斯
Smith.
很快  他将拥有毁灭这个世界的能力
Very soon, he is going to have the power to destroy this world.
但我相信他不会就此罢手  他做不到
But I believe he won't stop there. He can't.
不毁灭一切  他不会停手
He won't stop until there's nothing left at all.
他到底是什么
What is he?
他就是你
He is you.
你的对立面  相反数
Your opposite, your negative.
维持方程平衡的产物
The result of the equation trying to balance itself out.
如果我无法阻止他呢
And if I can't stop him?
不论你能否阻止  尼奥
One way or another, Neo...
战争都将结束
this war is going to end.
今晚  两个世界的未来掌握在你手里
Tonight, the future of both worlds will be in your hands...
或是他手里
or in his.
你怎么样  没事吧
How are you feeling? Are you all right?
给我点时间
I need time.
-意料之中  -罗兰舰长
- That figures. - Captain Roland.
-怎么了  玛姬  -是贝恩  他醒了
- What's up, Maggie? - Bane is. He's conscious.
很好  也许他能告诉我们答案
Good. Maybe he's got some answers.
真香啊
I love that smell.
我肯定会怀念这味道的
I sure am going to miss it.
-先知  -我知道
- Oracle. - I know.
我知道
I know.
萨蒂  亲爱的
Sati, honey.
拿上几块饼干跟赛拉弗走吧
Take a few cookies and go with Seraph.
我能回来吗  我还想来做客
Can I come back? I would like to come back.
-我也欢迎你来  -那明天见
- I would like that too. - Then I'll see you tomorrow.
希望如此  亲爱的  希望如此
I hope so, hon, I hope so.
我害怕  赛拉弗
I'm scared, Seraph.
过来
Come.
他还跟着我们
He's following us.
真是好久不见了
Well, well, it's been a long time.
我记得追踪你就如追踪鬼魂一般
I remember chasing you was like chasing a ghost.
我打败过你
I have beaten you before.
对  没错  但你也看到了
Yes, true, but as you can see,
今非昔比了
things are a little different now.
你就是最后的流亡者吧
And you must be the last exile.
-先知跟我说起过你  -真的吗
- The Oracle told me about you. - Really?
她说什么了
What did she say about me?
说你是个坏人
That you were a bad man.
等你了解了我  会发现我没有那么坏
Oh, I'm not so bad, once you get to know me.
无所不能的先知  我们终于见面了
The great and powerful Oracle, we meet at last.
我猜你一直在等我吧
I suppose you've been expecting me, right?
无所不知的先知从来不会惊讶
The all-knowing Oracle is never surprised.
她怎么可能惊讶  她知晓一切
How can she be? She knows everything.
但如果是真的
But if that's true,
为什么她知道我会来  还留在这儿
then why is she here if she knew I was coming?
她为什么不离开
Why wouldn't she leave?
也许你知道我会这么做  也许你不知道
Maybe you knew I would do that, maybe you didn't.
如果你知道  这说明
If you did, that means
你烤好了饼干  装盘放在那儿
you baked those cookies and set that plate there...
是故意的  有目的的
deliberately, purposefully...
这说明你坐在那儿
which means that you're sitting there
也是故意的  有目的的
also deliberately, purposefully.
你对萨蒂做了什么
What did you do with Sati?
"饼干也需要倾注爱"
"Cookies need love like everything does."
你是个混蛋
You are a bastard.
你最了解我  母亲
You would know, Mom.
做你该做的事吧
Do what you're here to do.
遵命  女士
Yes, ma'am.
我希望自己能帮得上忙
I really wish I could help,
但我  什么都记不起来了
but I just... I don't remember any of it.
你胳膊上的伤口呢
What about the cuts on your arms?
有的已经有好几天了
Those cuts are more than one day old.
对  肯定是
Yeah, definitely.
你说得没错  长官
You're right about that, Sir.
看起来是我自己弄伤的
They look like they might be self-inflicted.
但我为什么要伤害自己呢
But why would I do something like that to myself?
只有一个可能  我不是我
Unless, of course, I wasn't myself.
但如果我不是我  我又会是谁呢
But if I'm not me, then who am I?
查过震颤谵妄吗
Has this man been tested for VDTs?
查过  长官  结果为阴性
Yes, Sir. It was negative.
但他的神经活动很不正常
But he is showing a lot of unusual neural activity.
有跨突触激发  能看出最近受过创伤
Some cross-synaptic firing, as well as signs of recent trauma...
大脑皮质上都是最近才形成的疤痕组织
with fresh fibrotic scarring throughout the cortex.
我要知道真相
I want the truth.
不论采取什么手段  一定要让他想起来
I don't care what it takes. Make him remember.
长官  找到它了
Sir, we found her.
-罗果斯号吗  -是  长官
- The Logos? - Yes, Sir.
总算有点好消息了
About time we had some goddamn good news.
扫描到生命迹象了吗
Are the thermals picking up any signs of life?
没有  长官
No, Sir. Nothing yet.
船怎么样
What about the ship?
全息成像显示船体并无损伤
Holographic says the hull's still intact.
停下  派个人守在炮塔
Drop down and keep a man in the turret.
是  长官
Yes, Sir.
派人去搜索一遍
Get a full diagnostic on that ship
越快越好
as fast as humanly possible.
小心  长官
Careful, Sir.
混蛋乌贼都很狡猾  可能是陷阱
The squids are sneaky bastards. It could be a trap.
什么声音
What was that?
把那玩意都收起来  小伙子们
You can put that shit away, boys.
她只是启动不了了
All she needs is a jump.
-奈奥比  -墨菲斯
- Niobe. - Morpheus.
-你没事吧  -是的  我没事
- Are you all right? - Yes, I'm fine.
我们不知道那之后发生了什么...
We didn't know what happened after...
-对不起  -没关系
- I'm sorry. - It's okay.
我也很高兴见到你
I'm happy to see you too.
-你救出尼奥了吗  -是的
- Did you get Neo out? - Yes.
-你是怎么知道的  -是先知
- How did you know about that? - The Oracle.
-你见过她  -就在哨兵发现我们之前
- You saw her? - Just before the sentinels found us.
-她告诉你什么了  -一如既往
- What did she tell you? - The same thing she always does.
正是我需要听到的话
Exactly what I needed to hear.
12小时之内  机器就会进入船坞
In less than 12 hours, the machines will breach the dock walls.
所有的模拟结果都显示
Every simulation we've run,
一旦机器进入了城市
we've seen that once the machines are inside the city...
我们的存活几率会大幅下降
the odds of our survival decrease dramatically.
所以  我们的首要任务就是
Thus, our primary objective must be...
挖掘机钻入之后  尽快摧毁或废掉它
to destroy or disable the diggers inside the dock.
如果做到了  也许
If we can do that, perhaps
我们就能阻止它们进入城市
we can prevent them from ever reaching the city.
如果失败  我们就只能在神庙入口
If not, the only place we will be able to mount a defense...
殊死一搏了
will be at the entrance of the temple.
那里很狭窄  逼它们进入瓶颈
It is small and will force them into a bottleneck...
方便我们集中剩余的火力
allowing us to concentrate the remainder of our defense.
我们知道你还征集了志愿者
We understand that you've requested additional volunteers.
没错
That is correct.
要完成首要目标
Precisely what size force are you planning
你打算组织多少人手
to commit to the primary dock objective?
依现在的情况看  所有的武装机甲部队
Right now, the entire APU Corps
和一半的步兵
and half the infantry.
一半的步兵
Half the infantry?
如果由我做决定  议员
If it were up to me, Councillor...
我会号召所有的男人  女人和孩子
I'd take every man, woman and child,
让他们扛起枪
put a gun in their hand...
一起去守卫船坞
and march them into that dock.
幸好决定权不在你
Perhaps it is best that it is not up to you.
时间自会证明  议员
Time will tell, Councillor.
指挥官  还有个问题
Commander, just one more question.
尼布甲尼撒号有消息吗
Has there been word from the Nebuchadnezza?
没有  而且到这个地步
None, and at this point
我有理由相信永远都不会有了
there's no reason to expect there will be.
可能吧
Perhaps.
但我们还有希望
But we can hope.
只怕希望这种奢侈品我是无福消受了
I'm afraid hope is an indulgence I don't have time for.
-姿怡  你在干什么  -做炮弹
- Zee, what are you doing? - Making shells.
他们要疏散我们这层  得走了
They're evacuating our level. We have to go.
-我不会跟你走的  -什么
- I'm not going with you. - What?
他们在招募志愿者来守卫船坞
They've called for volunteers to hold the dock.
孩子们  待在这
Kids, you stay here.
我知道你的感受  但你不能这么做
I know how you feel, Zee, but you can't do this.
-我必须去  -为什么
- I have to. - Why?
因为我爱他
Because I love him.
我像他爱我那样爱他
I love him the same as he loves me.
而且如果我们互换处境
And if I were out there and he were here,
我知道他会怎么做
I know what he'd do.
但你会死的  这太疯狂了  姿怡
But you're gonna get yourself killed. It's crazy, Zee.
也许吧
Maybe it is.
但你问问自己  如果是为了多泽
But ask yourself, if it were Dozer...
你知道要想再见他
and you knew the only chance
必须要守住船坞
you had to see him was to hold the dock...
你会怎么做
what would you do?
做炮弹
Make shells.
这是怎么回事
What the shit is going on over here?
意外  长官  我没看到...
An accident, Sir. I didn't see...
-对不起  -你是什么人
- I'm sorry. - Who the hell are you?
一名志愿者  长官
A unit volunteer, Sir.
像你这种乳臭未干的小孩
What's a pod-born pencil-neck like you
到我的部队来添什么乱
doing volunteering for my Corps?
我想贡献力量  长官
I want to do my part, Sir.
我们得守住船坞
We gotta hold the dock.
-你多大  孩子  -18岁
- How old are you, kid? - Eighteen.
你要是说16岁  我没准就信了
Should have said 16, I might have believed that.
好吧  我16岁
Okay, I'm 16.
参军的最低年龄是18  16岁太小了
Minimum age for the Corps is 18. Sixteen's too young.
机器不会在乎我多大
The machines don't care how old I am.
一样会杀了我
They'll kill me just the same.
这倒是事实
Ain't that the goddamn truth.
给我个机会  长官  我不会让你失望
Give me a chance, Sir. I won't let you down.
如果你没做到
You do,
你会发现我和机器是有一些共同点的
and you'll find me and the machines have got something in common.
好了  给启动器充电
Okay, charge the igniter.
她又活过来了
She lives again.
需要我建立连接
You want to patch an uplink
帮你重新装载操作软件吗  火花
to reload the operations software, Sparky?
好啊  太好了
Yeah, that'd be swell.
顺便帮我擦下挡风玻璃吧
Could you clean the windshield while you're at it?
上传完毕  重新上线了
Uplinks in place. I'm bringing her back online.
一切正常  除了...
Looking good, except...
矩阵的信号出了点问题
something's wrong with the Matrix feed.
不  这里没问题
No, there's not.
我们看到的代码也不对劲
You're looking at what we're looking at.
那里到底怎么回事
What's the hell going on in there?
不论是什么  肯定不是好事
Whatever it is, it can't be good.
机器已攻占21号节点
The machines have taken Junction 21.
依我看  如果我们从这里深入地下网络
The way I see it, if we drop down from broadcast here...
153号交叉口
Intersect 153,
也许能打它们个措手不及
we might surprise them.
我们先上  尽可能攻到深处
We'll go first, hammer as deep as we can,
然后释放EMP
then blow our EMP.
希望我们能打开足够大的空间让你们通过
Hopefully we can punch a hole big enough for you to get through.
计划并不完美  但在我看来
It ain't pretty, but the way I see it,
这是回家的唯一办法
it's the only way back.
不  不是
No, it's not.
还有条路  一条补给线
There's another way. A support line.
从这里深入地下
It drops down right here,
比走21号节点近了一千米
1000 meters short of 21.
如果运气好  也许我们能
If we're lucky, we may be able
在它们还未发觉时进入
to slip down without them ever knowing.
那是条机械管线  根本不可能
That's a mechanical line. It's impossible.
没人能在机械管线里驾驶飞船
No one can pilot a mechanical.
我可以
I can.
-胡扯  -我开过
- Bullshit. - I've done it.
那是很久以前了  奈奥比
That was a long time ago, Niobe.
我说了我可以
I said I can do it.
那又怎样  只有你一人可以
So what? You'll be the only one that can.
我们绝对跟不上
There's no way we can follow you.
我知道时间紧迫
I know time is always against us.
抱歉我占用了好多时间
I'm sorry that I took so long.
-但我想先确定  -确定什么
- But I wanted to be sure. - Sure of what?
-我知道自己的使命了  -是什么
- I know what I have to do. - What?
三言两语没法解释清楚  我就直说了
There's no easy way to say this, so I'll just say it.
-我要开走一艘飞船  -什么
- I have to take one of the ships. - What?
去哪
To go where?
去机器城市
To the Machine City.
我知道你们很难理解
I know it's difficult to understand.
不难理解  你绝对是疯了
No, it's not. You're out of your goddamn mind.
我还是要去
I still have to go.
你不会成功的  一百年来
You'll never make it. In 100 years,
从没有飞船能接近它一百公里内
no ship has been within 100 kilometers of it.
-你绝对不会成功的  -我必须一试
- You'll never make it. - I have to try.
-是先知让你这么做的吗  -不是
- Is this what the Oracle has told you? - No.
真是愚蠢至极
This is asinine.
如果你想自杀  那就去吧
If you want to kill yourself, go do it...
但别浪费我们的飞船
but do it without wasting our ships.
-你得相信我  我必须去  -胡扯
- You have to believe me. I have to go. - Bullshit!
我是这里的舰长  去哪里得听我的
I am the Captain of this ship. I say where it has to go!
而且就算这艘船要下地狱
And I believe this ship will go to hell
我也不会让你把它开走
long before I let you take it anywhere.
-他可以开我的  -你不能这么做
- He can take mine. - You can't do that.
你自己刚说完  我自己的飞船
Don't even think of trying to tell me what I can or cannot do...
用不着你插手
with my ship after that little speech.
但是天啊  奈奥比
But for Christ's sake, Niobe...
我来开这艘船  我的船交给他
I'll pilot this ship, he can take mine.
如果我们整点前出发
If we leave inside the hour,
我们会跟那些机器同时抵达锡安
we should reach Zion as the machines do.
这计划就很不错了
That's as good a plan as any.
浪费  这就是无谓的浪费
It's a waste. A goddamn waste.
两艘船  两个方向
Two ships, two directions.
仿佛是天意  对吧  墨菲斯
Sounds like providence, doesn't it, Morpheus?
-你一向不信救世主  -我仍然不信
- You've never believed in the One. - I still don't.
那你为什么要这么做
Then why are you doing this?
因为我相信他
I believe in him.
谢谢
Thank you.
-这是干嘛的  -帮你放松
- What's that for? - To help you relax.
使你更容易回忆起来
To make it easier for you to remember.
要是我不想记起来呢
What if I don't want to remember?
你怎么会不想呢
Why would you want that?
如果EMP是我释放的呢
What if I blew that EMP?
要是那些船真的是我毁的
What if I did destroy those ships
那些人的死也是我造成的呢
and I am responsible for the deaths of all those men?
如果都是我
If I did that
我待在这就不怎么安全了  对吧
it wouldn't be very safe for me here, would it?
当然  你可能也不怎么安全
Of course, it might not be very safe for you either.
我准备好了
I'm ready.
崔妮蒂
Trinity
我要跟你说件事
there's something I have to say.
这件事你必须明白
Something you need to understand.
我只知道我非去不可
I know I'm supposed to go.
但是除此之外
But beyond that
我也说不准  我
I don't know. I...
我知道  你觉得自己有去无回
I know. You don't think you're coming back.
从你说你要走的那刻起我就知道了
I knew it the moment you said you had to leave.
你都写在脸上了
I could see it in your face.
就像是你看我的那瞬间
Just like you knew the moment
就知道我一定会跟你去
you looked at me that I was coming with you.
我害怕  崔妮蒂
I'm scared, Trin.
我也是
So am I.
我一只靴子就穿了十分钟
It took me 10 minutes to buckle up one boot.
但是我跟你说
But I'll tell you something.
六小时前  我对梅洛文基恩说
Six hours ago, I told the Merovingian
我愿意为你放弃所有
I was ready to give anything and everything for you.
你知道过去的六小时里发生了什么改变吗
Do you know what's changed in the last six hours?
不知道
No.
什么都没变
Nothing.
-弹药都装完了吗  -马上就好  长官
-You finished loading ammunition? - Just about, sir.
动作快点  我们没时间了
Let's move it. We are out of time.
不给他们留点什么吗
You're not leaving them anything?
他说他不需要
He said he didn't need it.
我要说的不是再见  而是祝好运
I ain't saying goodbye. I'm saying good luck.
谢谢
Thank you.
我只希望你知道你自己在做什么
I can only hope you know what you're doing.
我也是
Me too.
很荣幸认识您  长官
It was an honor, sir.
不  是我的荣幸
No, the honor is still mine.
-准备好了  长官  -终于好了
- We're ready, sir. - About damn time.
我们已经晚了  舰长  所以加把劲
We're already late, captain, so let's hit it and hit it hard.
再见  宝贝
Bye, baby.
照顾好他们
Take good care of them.
准备好了吗
Ready?
引擎还在运转
Engine's still firing.
肯定是点火器  我去看看
Must be a fuse. I'll check it out.
早该料到他会派你这个贱人来
I should've known he'd send his bitch first.
贝恩
Bane.
还没人能从我手下逃走这么多次
No one ever got away from me as many times as you did.
每一次我都以为是最后一次
Every single time, I thought it was the last.
每一次我都觉得肯定抓到你了
Every time, I was sure we had you,
但你还是从我们的指缝里溜走了
but somehow you'd slip through our fingers.
我真的说不出那有多让人懊恼
I really can't express just how aggravating that can be.
你在说什么呀
What are you talking about?
我想杀掉你会跟杀掉他一样有趣
I think I might enjoy killing you as much as killing him.
尼奥  是贝恩  他疯了
Neo, it's Bane. He's psychotic!
我会让你付出代价的
You're gonna pay for that.
还有二十七公里
Twenty-seven kilometers to go.
舰长  下面有紧急情况
Captain, we got an emergency down here.
-怎么了  AK  -是玛姬  长官
- What is it, AK? -It's Maggie, sir.
她死了  被杀了  我认为是贝恩干的
She's dead, murdered. I think it was Bane.
该死的
Goddamn it.
我就知道  我就知道他疯了
I knew it. I knew he was out of his goddamn mind.
是他释放的EMP
He fired that EMP.
该死的  我就应该逼他承认
Goddamn it, I should have beaten it out of him.
舰长  我们搜过整艘船了  他不在
We searched the whole ship, captain. He ain't here.
-我知道他在哪  -罗果斯号
- I know where he is. - The Logos.
-我们得回去  -太迟了
- We gotta go back. - Too late.
你怎么知道  万一他们需要我们帮忙呢
You don't know that. What if they need our help?
太危险了
It's too dangerous.
-为什么  -因为如果他们已经被杀了
- Why? - Because if he's killed them
那他就控制了另一个EMP
he'll control another EMP.
现在他们只能靠自己了  就像我们一样
At this point, they're on their own. Just like us.
安德森先生
Mr. Anderson.
你在这个世界里的行为
I see you are as predictable
跟在那个世界里一样好预测
in this world as you are in the other.
-你说什么  -他疯了
- What? - He's out of his mind.
你也许这么想  但是我和安德森先生知道
It might appear that way to you. But Mr. Anderson and I know
外表有时会欺骗你
that appearances can be deceiving.
困惑了吗  安德森先生
Confused, Mr. Anderson?
一会你就明白了
It'll all become clear in a moment.
谢谢你送枪来给我  就放那吧
Thank you for bringing me the gun. You can set it down right there.
别听他的
Don't do it.
开枪  快开
Shoot. Shoot now.
是啊  开啊  烧死我们  活活烧死我们吧
Yes, shoot. Fry us. Burn us alive.
开枪  不然的话  他会把咱俩都杀了
Do it. If you don't, he'll kill us both.
看看他  他知道他该开枪  但他做不到
Look at him. He knows he should do it, but he won't.
-他做不到  -开枪啊
- He can't. - Do it.
后退  然后转过身去
Back away from the gun and turn around.
放了她
Let her go.
这场景有点熟悉  对吧
Somehow familiar, isn't it?
咱俩经历过这一幕  记得吗
We've been here before, you and I, remember?
我记得  我就只想着这件事
I do. I think of nothing else.
-你是谁  -还认不出我吗
- Who are you? - Still don't recognize me?
我承认
I admit,
困在这么一个腐烂的躯壳里很难思考
it is difficult to even think encased in this rotting piece of meat.
每一次呼吸都闻得到腐臭味
The stink of it filling every breath,
这味道环绕着你  逃脱不掉
a suffocating cloud you can't escape.
恶心
Disgusting.
看看这身体脆弱得可悲
Look at how pathetically fragile it is.
这么脆弱的东西就不该存活
Nothing this weak is meant to survive.
-你想怎么样  -我想要的跟你一样
- What do you want? - I want what you want.
没错  这就对了  安德森先生
Yes. That's it, Mr. Anderson.
看穿肉体
Look past the flesh.
透过我这双浑浊的双眼
Look through the soft gelatin
看看你的敌人
of these dull cow eyes and see your enemy.
-不  -是的  安德森先生
- No. - Oh, yes, Mr. Anderson.
-这不可能  -没有我去不了的地方
- It can't be. - There's nowhere I can't go.
你躲到天涯海角我都能找到你
There is nowhere I won't find you.
-这不可能  -不是不可能
- It's impossible. - Not impossible.
是逃不掉的
Inevitable.
永别了  安德森先生
Goodbye, Mr. Anderson.
就是这个  必须是这个
This is it. It's gotta be.
不
Oh, no.
真希望你能看到你自己  安德森先生
I wish you could see yourself, Mr. Anderson.
瞎眼的救世主
Blind messiah.
你就是你们人类的象征  安德森先生
You're a symbol for all of your kind, Mr. Anderson.
无助
Helpless.
可悲
Pathetic.
等着别人结束你们的痛苦
Just waiting to be put out of your misery.
我能看见你
I can see you.
这事还没完  安德森先生
It's not over, Mr. Anderson.
这事还没完
It's not over.
-崔妮蒂  -尼奥
- Trinity! - Neo.
尼奥
Neo.
不  你的眼睛
Oh, no. Your eyes.
我会没事的
I'll be okay.
没事的  崔妮蒂
It's all right, Trin.
但是你得驾驶飞船了
But I think you're gonna have to drive.
地动检测预计机器22分钟后钻入
Seismic's projecting 22 minutes to breach.
他们不可能知道我们没有EMP
They can't know we don't have an EMP.
肯定会一波波进攻
They'll have to attack in waves.
火力集中在挖掘机上
Concentrate our offense on the diggers.
让武装机甲就位
Order the APUs into position.
是  长官
Yes, sir.
快点  快点
Come on, move.
好了
All right!
时候到了
This is it.
你们都了解我  所以我就长话短说了
Now, you all know me, so I'll just say this as simple as I can.
如果我们注定要死  那就是现在
If it's our time to die, it's our time.
我只请求大家  就算要死在这些混蛋手上
All I ask is, if we have to give these bastards our lives
也要先给他们点颜色看看
we give them hell before we do!
-你害怕吗  查拉  -当然了
- You scared, Charra? - Shit, yeah.
但是我要跟你约定
But I'll make you a deal.
你负责上膛  我负责开火
You keep loading, I keep shooting.
成交
Deal.
-上帝啊  看看那个  -安静
- Holy Christ, would you look at that. - Quiet.
-离裂缝还有多远  -1.4公里
- How far to the opening? - 1.4 kilometers.
我们的发热量还是太大了
We're still generating too hot a field.
幽灵  关掉所有辅助系统
Ghost, kill all auxiliary systems.
全手动  关掉四个悬浮推进器
Give me full manual. Drop down four pads.
会降到底下的
It'll bottom out.
-稳住  宝贝  -还有七百米
- Easy, baby. - Seven hundred meters.
只要我们能靠得够近...
If we can just get close enough...
六百米
Six hundred meters.
到了
There.
该死
Shit!
-它们来了  -系统全部启动
- Jig's up, here they come. - Give me full power, full systems.
去炮台  每个炮台都要有人  快去
Man the gun turrets, every goddamn one of them. Go!
幽灵  你是最好的炮手  跟他们去
Ghost, you're the best gunner we have, go with them.
墨菲斯  你来替他
Morpheus, take his place.
我来了  宝贝
I'm coming, baby.
它们来了
Here they come.
慢点开  这可不是罗果斯号
Slow down, this ain't the Logos.
别把午饭吐出来  罗兰  出发了
Hang on to your lunch, Roland, here we go.
我的天  这飞船还能这么开
Holy Christ, I didn't know this ship could do that.
机器钻入船坞了
Breach! The dock is breached!
举枪
Knuckle up!
为了锡安
For Zion!
该死
Shit.
走  咱们走
Come on, let's go.
背靠背
Knuckle up!
上弹
Reload!
9号机甲上弹
Reload nine!
快  快  快去  快去
Go, go! Move, move!
小心左边
Watch your left!
别让它们过去
Don't let them through!
祖卡
Zuka!
天啊
Oh, my God.
我的步兵团死哪去了
Where the hell's my infantry?
给我干掉那该死的钻头
I want that goddamn machine taken down!
喜欢[钻]这个吧
Dig this!
该死
Oh, shit!
-二号怪物钻至洞口  -该死
- Bogey Two at the breach point! - Goddamn it!
该死  她屁股还真肥
Shit, she's got a fat ass.
把它们弄下去
Keep them off me!
天啊  这玩意到处都是
Christ, there's a shitstorm of them.
-舰长  看到没  -它们朝无线电去了
- Captain, you see that? - They're after the radio.
阻止它们
Stop them!
该死
Damn it!
好了
Yeah.
抓住我的腰带
Grab my belt.
给我让开一下就好
Just give me one clean shot.
该死
Damn it!
查拉
Charra!
-有东西来了  -船坞上到处都是
- I got incoming! - We got a dock full of incoming!
-是  长官  可这次不同  -怎么了
- Yes, sir. But this is different, sir. - What?
这好像是自己人  长官
I think it's one of ours, sir.
-不可能  -全息系统正在确认
- That's impossible. - Holographics are trying to confirm.
联系他们  我要对口令
Contact them. I want access codes.
正在联系  长官  可是没有应答
We're trying, sir. There's no response.
这是陷阱  不可能是自己人
It's a trick. That's not one of ours, it can't be.
那是机械管线  没人能驾船走那条路
That's a mechanical line. No one can pilot mechanical.
-船尾向前  30度  80%  -30度  80%
- Forward aft, 30 degrees at 80 percent. - Thirty degrees, 80.
-右舷下转60度  20%  -60度
- Lower starboard 60 degrees, 20 percent. - Sixty degrees.
-该死  快跟上  -我尽力了
- Shit! Come on, keep up! - I'm trying!
长官  全息系统已确认  是汉默号
Sir, holographic confirms. It's the Hammer,sir.
这怎么可能
How can that be?
汉默号正受到攻击  船身严重受损
The ship is under attack, sustaining heavy damage.
但以其现有速度
But at its present velocity,
将在12分钟后抵达三号门
it'll reach Gate Three in 12 minutes.
长官  他们的EMP可以干掉外面的所有乌贼
Sir, their EMP could take out every sentinel out there.
不止  还会毁掉我们的防御系统
It'd take out more than that. It'll wipe out our defense system.
要是在里面释放EMP  船坞就保不住了
We blow an EMP inside, we will lose the dock.
长官  船坞已经失守了
Sir, we already lost the dock.
开门
Open the gate.
三号门无反应  我们严重受损  长官
Gate Three is not responding! We've taken critical damage, sir!
门没法控制  打不开了
We've lost control! We can't open it!
出口到了
There's the exit.
等我信号  全速前进
On my mark, give me full power
右舷朝左下方转90度
90 degrees to lower-left starboard.
全速前进
Full power
90度
ninety degrees.
就是现在
Now!
坚持住  宝贝
Hold on, baby.
我的天  小妞  你还真有两下子
Goddamn, woman, you can drive.
还没到家呢  大门情况如何
We ain't home yet. What about the gate?
乌贼进入船坞了
Sentinels are inside the dock.
我们太迟了吗
Are we too late?
-还有多少武装机甲  -13台  长官
- How many APUs are operational? - Thirteen, sir.
给我接离三号门最近的
Get me the one closest to Gate Three.
上弹
Reload!
子弹用得太快了
He's pissing metal.
快去
Go!
小心  它们要过来了
Heads up! They're coming around!
在你身后
Behind you!
卡住了
It's jammed!
别弄了  孩子  快离开这
Forget it, kid! Get out of here!
好了
Got it!
米弗尼舰长
Captain Mifune.
不
Oh, no.
他们来了
They're coming.
汉默号
The Hammer.
什么
What?
你得把门打开
You have to open that gate.
把配重打掉
Cut the counterweights.
你能做到的
You can do it.
快点  没时间了
Hurry. There's no time.
舰长
Captain,
我都没完成训练课程
I didn't finish the training program.
我也没有
Neither did I.
-把它关掉  -关掉上弹机
- Lock that down! - Kill the feeder!
我们坚持不住了  得释放EMP了
We won't make it. We gotta blow the EMP now.
拜托  快来个人
Come on, someone, please.
重心要前倾
Keep the weight forward.
像羽毛一样轻盈
Light as a feather.
指挥官  全息系统显示
Commander, holographic reports
米弗尼舰长的机甲重新上线  正走向三号门
Captain Mifune's APU is up and moving to Gate Three.
扳机不要扣得太死
Don't over-squeeze the trigger.
米弗尼舰长的机甲已经抵达三号门
Captain Mifune's APU just reached Gate Three.
-还有多久  -还有两分钟抵达
- How much time? - Two minutes to impact.
米弗尼舰长  收到吗
Captain Mifune, do you copy?
他的无线电好像已经失灵了  长官
I think his radio is down, sir.
米弗尼
Mifune,
我是洛克
this is Lock.
不知道你能不能听到  如果你听到
I don't know if you can hear me, but if you can...
汉默号还有两分钟就到了
the Hammer's two minutes away.
你还有两分钟的时间打开大门
You've got two minutes, captain, to get that gate open.
林克
Link.
到主甲板上去  给EMP充能
Get to the main deck! Charge the EMP!
开枪吧  孩子
Do it, kid.
尼奥  我相信
Neo. I believe.
-太棒了  -能穿过去吗
- Yes! - Can we make it?
必须能穿过去
We ain't come this far.
马上到家了  马上到家了
Almost home, almost home.
发射  林克
Burn it, Link!
-你成功了  -不
- You did it. - No.
是我们成功了
We did it.
你是个出色的驾驶员
You're a hell of a pilot.
这个世上有些事是不会变的
Some things in this world never change.
但有些事会变吗
But some things do?
幸好
Luckily,
有些事会变
some things do.
林克
Link!
-姿怡  姿怡  -林克
- Zee? Zee! - Link!
我就知道你会回来  我就知道
I knew you'd come. I knew it.
我向你保证过的
I made a promise.
你真的戴了
You did wear it.
开玩笑吗  我这辈子都不摘下来了
Are you kidding? I'm never gonna take it off.
三位舰长  只剩一艘船
Three captains, one ship.
我看另两艘船
I'll assume the other ships
都白白牺牲掉了吧
were lost under equally pointless circumstances.
见到你我也很高兴  杰森
Good to see you too, Jason.
议会正等着听你们的解释
The Council's waiting to hear an explanation.
抱歉我不能一起出席
You'll forgive me for not attending,
因为我还要收拾这个烂摊子
but I have to try to salvage this debacle.
我是不是听错了  指挥官
Did I miss something, Commander?
我们不是拯救了船坞吗
I thought we saved the dock.
你们这些人都是这样
That's the problem with you people.
眼光永远放不远
You can't think but five minutes in front of you.
那一发EMP
That EMP knocked out
废掉了所有的电器  所有的机甲
almost every piece of hardware and every APU.
如果换做是我
If I were the machines,
我会把所有乌贼都派来
I'd send every sentinel I have here right now.
你拯救船坞了吗  舰长
Save the dock, captain?
你是把船坞拱手让出去了
You handed it to them on a silver platter.
快点  尽快切断
Come on, get it cut.
主桥清理完毕
The bridge is clear.
你听到了吗
Do you hear that?
快把线缆接好
Get that cable run!
我希望系统尽快恢复运作
I want the system back online!
指挥官  是船坞那边  有敌情
Commander, it's the dock. They've got incoming.
命令所有人撤回来
Order everyone to fall back.
封住通道  马上
Seal the shaft. Now.
快撤
Move it!
我的天哪
Oh, my God.
-全员撤离  -起爆吧
- All clear. - Do it.
-快  快走  -起爆
- Go! Come on! Run! - Go!
该你了
Your move.
你把你的飞船给了他们
So you gave them your ship?
是的  议员
That is correct, councillor, I did.
你知道他们打算做什么
Knowing what he planned to do with it?
先知没说什么吗
The Oracle said nothing of this?
她告诉我尼奥会需要我的帮助
She told me Neo would need my help,
等他开口时  我必须选择帮还是不帮
and when the time came, I would choose to help him or not.
但是就那一艘飞船
But what hope can a single
能穿透机器的层层防线吗
vessel have against their entire defense system?
没希望  根本不可能  但他就是不听
None. It's completely impossible. But he wouldn't listen.
他连弹药都不要
He wouldn't even take any ammunition.
根本就是脑袋坏掉了
He was totally out of his goddamn mind.
不  他不是
No, he wasn't.
尼奥只是在遵循他坚持的信念
Neo is doing what he believes he must do.
我不知道他的做法是对是错  我也不知道
I don't know if what he's doing is right. I don't know...
他能否到达机器之城
if he'll reach the machine city.
就算他真的到达了
And if he does,
我也不知道他能不能拯救我们
I don't know what he can do to save us.
但我知道的是
But I do know that as long
只要他还有一口气在
as there is a single breath in his body...
就绝不会放弃
he will not give up.
我们也不能放弃
And neither can we.
气温在下降
Temperature's dropping.
要出去了
Here we go.
我们在发电厂上空  是不是
We're over the fields, aren't we?
你怎么知道的
How do you know that?
我能感觉到他们
I can feel them.
那边
Over there.
我们走那边  你看见那三条管线了吗
There's our path. Can you see it? Three lines.
输电线
Power lines.
沿着它们走
Follow them.
他们在干什么
What are they doing?
不知道
I don't know.
中尉
Lieutenant?
该死
Goddamn it.
现在怎么办  指挥官
What do we do now, commander?
只是迟早的事了
It is now a matter of time.
机器大军会钻透外墙
The machines will breach the walls of this city.
我强烈建议议会
I recommend that the Council join
随其他非军事人员一起撤往神庙
the other non-military personnel inside the temple.
还剩多少时间
How long do we have?
两小时  也许更少
Two hours. Maybe less.
我已派人在入口处造防御工事
My men have begun to fortified the entrance
留了足够的武器作最后抵抗
with enough artillery to make our last stand.
但我也力尽于此了
Beyond that, there isn't anything more I can do.
指挥官  你觉得我们有幸存的可能吗
Commander, do you think that we have any chance of surviving?
在我看来  该回答您问题的人不是我
If I were you, I wouldn't ask me that question.
而是他
I would ask him.
-为什么  -因为是他相信奇迹
- Why? - He's the one who believes in miracles.
前面  那些山脉
There. Those mountains.
就是那
That's it.
-你看见前面有什么了吗  -看到了
- Do you see what's out there? - Yes.
如果你告诉我能行的  我就相信你
If you tell me we'll make it, I'll believe you.
我们能行的
We'll make it.
必须成功
We have to.
哨兵来了
Sentinels.
它们太多了
There's too many!
抓住你了
Gotcha!
-加油尼奥  你得帮我  -我打不过他们
- Come on Neo, I need help here! - I can't beat them.
-那怎么办  -飞上去  从上面越过去
- What do we do? - Go up, over them.
-什么  -天空  只有这条路可走
- What? - The sky! It's the only way.
那就飞上去
Then up we go.
好美啊
Beautiful.
给启动器充电  把船发动起来
Pump the igniter. The ship will start.
再来  慢一点
Again. Slowly.
现在
Now!
崔妮蒂
Trin?
Trinity?
崔妮蒂
-我在这  -在哪
- I'm here. - Where?
这边
Here.
我们成功了
We made it.
你说过会成功的
You said we would.
真是难以置信  崔妮蒂
It's unbelievable, Trin.
到处金光闪烁
Light everywhere.
仿佛整座城都是光构成的
Like the whole thing was built of light.
我真希望你也能看到
I wish you could see what I see.
你带我见识得够多了
You've already shown me so much.
怎么了崔妮蒂  哪里不对吗
What is it, Trinity? What's wrong?
我不能再陪着你了  尼奥
I can't go with you, Neo.
我的路已经到了尽头
I've gone as far as I can.
什么
What?
不
Oh, no.
不  不
Oh, no. No, no.
没事的
It's all right.
到时候了
It's time.
我能做的都做了
I've done all that I could do.
剩下的就交给你了
Now you have to do the rest.
你必须坚持到底
You have to finish it.
你必须拯救锡安
You have to save Zion.
我做不到
I can't.
-没有你我不行  -你当然行
- Not without you. - Yes, you can.
你一定行
You will.
我相信你行  我一直坚信
I believe it. I always have.
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
崔妮蒂  你不能死
Trinity, you can't die.
别死
You can't.
你不会死的
我当然会死
Yes, I can.
你救过我一次
You brought me back once.
这次怕是不行了
But not this time.
你还记得...
Do you remember...
在那大厦顶上  你接住我之后
on that roof, after you caught me...
我对你说的最后一句话吗
the last thing I said to you?
你说  "抱歉了"
You said, "I'm sorry."
真希望我没说
I wish I hadn't.
那是我最后的念头
That was my last thought.
我希望我还有机会...
I wished I had one more chance...
说出更重要的话
to say what really mattered.
告诉你我有多爱你
To say how much I loved you.
告诉你我多么感激和你在一起的每一刻
How grateful I was for every moment I was with you.
但等我终于知道如何开口
But by the time I knew how to say what I wanted to,
已经太晚了
it was too late.
但你把我救了回来
But you brought me back.
你让我心愿成真
You gave me my wish.
你给了我一次吐露心声的机会
One more chance to say what I really wanted to say.
吻我吧
Kiss me.
再吻我...
Once more...
一次吧
kiss me.
把弹药运到地方
Get that ammunition where it belongs!
限你一次装配好
You got one chance to get this right.
快把那玩意架起来
Get that damn thing mounted!
-快  -我们走  快撤快撤
- Hurry. - Let's go, let's go, let's go!
尼奥...
Neo...
如果你打算做点什么  最好快点
if you're gonna do something, do it quick.
我只想把该说的话说完
I only ask to say what I've come to say.
之后我任你处置  绝不反抗
After that, do what you want, and I won't try and stop you.
说吧
Speak.
史密斯这个程序已经不受你控制
The program Smith has grown beyond your control.
他很快就会占领这座城市  像他占领矩阵一样
He will spread through this city as he spread through the Matrix.
你阻止不了他
You cannot stop him.
-但我能  -我们不需要你
- But I can. - We don't need you!
我们什么都不需要
We need nothing!
如果你说的是真的  那是我想错了
If that's true, then I've made a mistake,
现在杀了我吧
and you should kill me now.
你想要什么
What do you want?
和平
Peace.
它们干什么
What are they doing?
你又在干什么
What are you doing?
墨菲斯
Morpheus!
如果你失败了呢
And if you fail?
不会的
I won't.
是尼奥
Neo.
他在为我们而战
He fights for us.
安德森先生  欢迎归来
Mr. Anderson, welcome back.
我们很想你
We missed you.
你喜欢我对这的改造吗
You like what I've done with the place?
今晚该结束了
It ends tonight.
这我知道  我预见到了
I know it does. I've seen it.
因此其余的我都来观战
That's why the rest of me is just going to enjoy the show...
因为我们都知道  我会击败你
because we already know that I'm the one that beats you.
你感觉到了吗  安德森先生...
Can you feel it, Mr. Anderson...
它在逼近你
closing in on you?
我感觉得到
Oh, I can.
这我得谢谢你  毕竟是你用生命...
I really should thank you for it. After all, it was your life...
教会了我所有生命的意义
that taught me the purpose of all life.
生命的意义就是终结
The purpose of life is to end.
为什么  安德森先生
Why, Mr. Anderson?
为什么  到底为什么
Why, why, why?
你到底为什么
Why do you do it?
为什么  为什么爬起来
Why? Why get up?
还抗争什么
Why keep fighting?
你相信自己在为什么而战吗
Do you believe you're fighting for something?
为了比生命更宝贵的东西吗
For more than your survival?
你能告诉我是什么吗  你真的知道吗
Can you tell me what it is? Do you even know?
是自由  还是真相
Is it freedom or truth?
还是和平  难道是爱
Perhaps peace? Could it be for love?
那是幻觉  安德森先生  都是假象
Illusions, Mr. Anderson. Vagaries of perception.
无非是人类低下的智力
Temporary constructs of a feeble human intellect...
给没有意义和目的的事物
trying desperately to justify
拼凑出的存在的借口
an existence that is without meaning or purpose!
那一切都像矩阵一样  是假的
And all of them as artificial as the Matrix itself...
不过也只有人类的意识
although only a human mind
才能创造出爱这种无聊的幻觉
could invent something as insipid as love.
你心里肯定是明白的
You must be able to see it,
安德森先生  现在你肯定懂了
Mr. Anderson. You must know it by now.
你赢不了  继续打下去毫无意义
You can't win. It's pointless to keep fighting.
为什么  安德森先生  你为什么要坚持
Why, Mr. Anderson, why? Why do you persist?
因为我选择如此
Because I choose to.
这是我的世界  我的世界
This is my world! My world!
慢着
Wait.
我预见过这一幕
I've seen this.
就是现在  这就是终点
This is it. This is the end.
没错  你就那样躺在那
Yes. You were laying right there, just like that.
而我
And I...
就站在这里  好像该说些什么
I stand here, right here, and I'm supposed to say something.
我说  "万物有始者必有终  尼奥"
I say, "Everything that has a beginning has an end, Neo."
什么  我说什么了
What? What did I just say?
不对  这完全不对  不该是这样
No, no. This isn't right. This can't be right.
离我远点
Get away from me!
你怕什么
What are you afraid of?
这是你的诡计
It's a trick.
你说得对  史密斯
You were right, Smith.
你总是对的
You were always right.
我逃不掉的
It was inevitable.
结束了吗
Is it over?
不  不  不
Oh, no, no, no.
这不公平
No, it's not fair.
成功了
It is done.
这不可能
It doesn't make sense.
他做到了
He did it.
他救了我们
He saved us.
结束了  他成功了  他成功了
It's over! He did it! He did it!
他成功了  战争结束了
He did it! It's over!
战争结束了  他成功了  成功了
It's over! He did it! He did it!
怎么了  发生什么了
What is it? What happened?
先生  他成功了  尼奥做到了
Sir, he did it, sir. Neo, he did it.
-做到什么了  -他结束了战争
- Did what? - He ended the war.
机器大军撤走了
The machines, they're gone.
战争结束了  先生  战争结束了
The war is over, sir. The war is over.
锡安  锡安
Zion! Zion!
锡安  结束了
Zion, it's over!
结束了
It's over!
战争结束了
The war is over!
我梦想着这一刻...
I have imagined this moment...
想了好久
for so long.
这是真的吗
Is this real?
尼奥  不管你在哪...
Neo, wherever you are...
谢谢你
thank you.
早上好
Good morning.
你觉得惊讶吗
Well, now. Ain't this a surprise.
你这一步走得真险
You played a very dangerous game.
改变总是很危险
Change always is.
你觉得这次和平能持续多久
Just how long do you think this peace is going to last?
能维持多久算多久
As long as it can.
其他人怎么办
What about the others?
什么其他人
What others?
那些希望离开的人
The ones that want out.
显然我会放他们自由
Obviously, they will be freed.
你保证吗
I have your word?
你以为我是什么  人类吗
What do you think I am? Human?
先知
Oracle!
我们还担心找不到你了呢
We were afraid we might not find you.
现在一切都好了
Everything's okay now.
看啊  看啊
Look, look.
哎呀  快瞧瞧
Just look at that.
好美啊
Beautiful.
是你的杰作吗
Did you do that?
纪念尼奥
For Neo.
太好了
That's nice.
他肯定很喜欢
I know he'd love it.
我们还能见到他吗
Will we ever see him again?
我觉得会
I suspect so.
总有一天
Someday.
你预见到了吗
Did you always know?
不  我没有
Oh, no. No, I didn't.
但我相信
But I believed.
我相信
I believed.